software engineering radio episode 48
interview with Drago's malesko
[Music]
welcome everybody to this new episode of
software engineering radio in this
episode we talked to Drago's mano Lesko
gravis is an architect with Microsoft's
patterns and practices group
I talked to Drago's about architectural
evaluation architecture evaluation is
about finding out whether an
architecture suits all the needs of the
various stakeholders that are involved
in an architecture before we actually
start with interview I wanted to point
out that this interview has been
recorded at the Java conference more
specifically it has been recorded in the
restaurant in the hotel and you can hear
that because in the background there is
some guy cleaning up the dishes and
making noise I don't think it's really
bad you can still easily hear what we're
talking about just wanted to point out
what the background noise is all about
so um let's get started welcome Drago's
to this episode of software engineering
radio hi Markus thank you
good to be here yeah welcome no problem
so um architecture evaluation so what is
it about and what is architecture for
that matter oh I'm not gonna open that
can of worms I learned my lesson a while
back it seems like nobody agrees what
architecture is and if you ask different
people you're gonna come up with
different responses and I usually use as
an excuse the fact that if you go to the
sei website and you look around we have
a long list with definitions there are
50 some or 60 some definitions so rather
than my incrementing the number I just
send you there and you look at it but
I'm yeah I'm pretty much in agreement
with the definition that the sei folks
have given I like actually their work in
this space and it revolves around the
components and the interaction between
the component between these components
and the properties that the components
and the connectors between the
components have mm-hm
you'll you'll find it there okay so
architecture evaluation then probably
has to do with kind of evaluating
whether the structure the components
interaction of the system are able to
meet some of the requirements that's
right as our systems have
changed significantly since about 10
years or 15 years ago many more concerns
are on a table now so if you think how
you were building systems back in 1985
or even 1981 you weren't that concerned
about multiple users distributed
computing networks security and so on
well those things have changed now most
of the systems that I build and I'm sure
that the ones that you're involved with
this well involve web and distribution
and multi users and multiple servers and
so on so once you bring all these
concerns to the table you need to be
careful about how you partition the
functionality in your applications how
do they communicate with each other how
they interact and interplay between
these components to achieve critical
goals that you are expecting and
architecture evaluation deals with
providing you a chance to assess how
well does the architecture support the
characteristics that the business people
or whoever the customers may not be an
architecture built for business people
for business purposes so how closely
does the architecture meet those those
goals those goals are things like
performance or security or conceptual
integrity if you want to get towards
more the the more esoteric ones or
subsets ability and so on so so you're
dealing more with these what many people
call non-functional requirements kind of
that's right there's a there's a lot of
non-functional requirements architecture
violation doesn't really really focus on
functionality per se that's something
that you would you would involve
different techniques architecture
evaluation
deals with verifying verifying that the
functionalities have been carved out
correctly which would be the functional
requirements the functionality of the
components so I have a component it
implements caching I have a component
that stores information like a database
I have a component that deals with user
input these are the components and I
want to make sure that the way I have
partition the functionality between
these components does not hamper my
achieving some of the architecture goals
which were these ill at ease if you will
the non-functional non-functional
characteristics we talked about these in
previous episodes extensively so our
listeners know
good so let's try to do this
systematically so what are some of the
preconditions or prerequisites that
projects must have or show in order for
architecture evaluation our use is
useful or feasible mm-hmm so there are
several it probably helps to step back
and look at when would you want to
evaluate an architecture why in why
correct and the the there are multiple
places in time where you want to do that
ideally you do it once you have made
some of these significant decisions and
you're not validated their arthritis
scissors and before you've written no
reams of code and and the cost of
undoing what you've done
becomes prohibitive there are other
places in the lifecycle of product when
you would want to do this and they would
be later on when things don't seem to
work as planned
typically no people call on on others to
evaluate your architectures and validate
their design choices and so on all the
way to the end but no the closer you get
to the end the high the the higher the
cost of making the change is going to be
if you say that you should do this
ideally as early as possible which is
obviously a useful thing then this
requires then you have that you have
some kind of upfront architectural
design so you have this you know big
upfront design before it's not implement
how does this go together with agile
development where you don't really do
this mm-hmm actually it doesn't require
big upfront design it it requires some
without thinking it was I'm thinking
ahead of time and let me first walk you
the process and then listen let's make
it out to get back to it because there's
a there's a very close parallel between
architecture valuation and agile
development that I would like to
emphasize this is actually a question
that many people ask me about and let's
let's revisit a topic later on okay so
inevitably you can you you typically
would like to valid your architecture
earlier to make sure that the design
change that you've made our sound and
they are aligned with whatever the
stakeholders over the architecture want
and there are several prerequisites for
this one prerequisite is that you have
some understanding with the people who
commissioned the architecture about what
is that they will get out of it
typically people tend to assume that
architecture valuation is something that
focuses only on the technology aspects
that is wrong and you need to reset
expectations and explain to them that
you will be looking beyond just the
technological choices for example some
on some projects that I have evaluated
initially the expectation was that well
have a look at my observational mapping
and my database choice and tell me
whether those are good choice or not
well there's not really architect
evaluation that's more product product
validation because if you get back to my
definition of protection of partitioning
of functionality and responsibilities
between the components by the time you
already have a database in the cache and
what have you before the partition of
functionality so I can only I can only
see whether something matches a
particular piece of functionality that
you have in the big picture or not
you're working more on a conceptual
architectural level that's right talk
about modules and interactions and
interaction patterns and and
distribution instead of X technology and
Y technology that's right you can think
about it in terms of CRC cards so one
way to think about it is that these
modules have some responsibilities what
is that they do they may be data
repository or maybe they may be caches
that help you save time by storing
intermediate results so you want have to
perform expensive computations in so i/o
and they also collaborate with other
modules and the amount of collaboration
and in interaction between these
components determines how the
architecture would fare up as far as
performance is concerned response time
throughput security and so on so that's
that's a rehash of the definition that I
brought up earlier yep all right and I
know important step probably you talked
before about involving stakeholders and
I guess being aware of these of who
these stakeholders are it's an important
prerequisite I guess that's right there
would be the second stage be before we
get to that point let's let's look at
the prerequisites so the first one was
to explain
what the expectations are what the
process entails what the outcome is
going to be so people will have a pretty
good understanding of their involved
involvement the types of artifacts that
the architecture of election will
deliver and so on the second thing that
you need to do as far as this
preparatory work the prerequisites is
concern is reviewing the architecture
artifacts that people have and yes the
architecture descriptions because when
you evaluate an architecture typically
if you do it early and it's not a lot of
coded you can look at but there should
be some some understanding of the domain
what what you're dealing with of the
business case how what's the
architecture business business in it
what are the architecture business
scenario what are the needs of the
stakeholders and so on so you need to
review that work and typically you end
up you end up doing a lot of work that
that you would need before embarking on
architecture evaluation yeah because
just because these artifacts don't exist
sometimes they do exist typically when
people apply processes like rap so they
start with good intentions they start
with a process that's more or less more
or less you know accepted out there they
they perform the work and these
artifacts exists so what are good
artifacts what are good ways of
describing an architecture not just for
making it amenable for a review or
evaluation but in general what do you
think is useful is UML useful or
metamodels architecture met amongst a
good thing or many ideas there well the
UML is just a representation absolutely
of an abstraction so if we if just one
representation is sufficient for the
particular abstraction that the
architecture represents then UML is
sufficient however in practice just one
representation for the abstraction that
the Destroyers anybody architecture is
not sufficient you need more so other
things that I've seen in the past would
be besides UML views that show you the
components and the relationships between
them and the way they interact so static
and dynamic views would be an
articulation of the architecture
business cycle so how do we get to
building to building the architecture
how Chris Arnold yes exactly exactly the
the
the envisioning the envisioning state of
the process as well as all these views
and in the sumption assumptions and
constraints that the architecture must
deal with some assumptions may be
revolving around who's gonna be
performing the work what kind of skill
sets they have some constraints may
involve components that you already have
in house and you want to use or you have
to use in so on so that's primarily
plain text stuff then how would this
information again how this information
is formatted or represented that doesn't
doesn't matter no and here it doesn't
but in practice you have to extract the
knowledge about the architecture
somewhere and there might be renderings
that are more suitable because they're
more formal or others you know so I mean
you have to write it down somehow right
so as far as the formatting is concerned
you will notice the white variants not
only on the quality in in depth of this
information but it'll also notice a wide
range of artifacts you could have
something formal like UML diagram so you
can have something very formal
maybe diagrams on the back of an
envelope now there would be an extreme
case but it is not not not of not a
specific format just be prepared to deal
with this variance okay so then the
other the other thing that you need to
look into as far as this meeting the
prerequisites is concern is to go beyond
the the step outside of the IT
department and see what exactly the
drivers are behind the architecture yeah
drivers yeah yeah
in many cases unfortunately if you take
a closer look you will see that the
drivers behind building a new
architecture purely technical sometimes
the IT just is looking for an excuse to
play with a new tool it's remove the new
technology play with frameworks and so
on and take take SOA many many projects
these days they embark on SOA without
having a really really strong need
everybody says that SOA is business
driven yes but if you if you look at it
and this happened to me on many many
instances while performing evaluations
for various clients just starting to
look into the architecture quickly
becomes clear very clear that the
business doesn't really is not really
interested in in exposing their services
to trading partners they are also not
interested in outsourcing their their
the functionality that the the business
entails right now to outside partners
and they don't really think in terms of
business processes that they want to
change very very quickly because maybe
it's it's a it's a business that has a
long way to go to articulate these
business processes so in that case
trying to drive down this nail with the
SOA hammer is going to be a waste of
time and resources yeah yeah so okay so
understanding the motivation for an
architecture even if it is that IT
department wants to play with it which
is also you know to some extent okay if
everybody agrees that this is a good
thing
understanding these things is probably
the most important thing in order to be
able to evaluate the architecture
absolutely the the IT is a big part of
the picture but they're not the only
stakeholders architectures have multiple
stakeholders the ite is an important
player but there are other stakeholders
and if if it turns out that the ite s
concerns are the prevalent ones then
it's okay to just satisfy those those
requirements and go with whatever
direction they want to pursue typically
what happens you get multiple viewpoints
in try to find a median point that
satisfies all these stakeholders and
we'll talk about it later on so other
things that that you want to do is to
make sure that you connect back to the
business problem even if even if the
architecture business case has been
clearly articulated at the beginning
what happens in time due to erosion or
just plain attention deficit disorder
from the side of the IT is that this
this business case gets distorted and
forgotten and people no longer are
thinking in terms that have been
articulated in the past so if you find
yourself on a project that here's some
something some work done on this front
try and revive it back pull it out and
make sure that it's still valid updated
and people are still aware of what
you're dealing with so that means all
involving the non IT stakeholders all
over the process what one classic I
think I know from my projects is that
the deployment and operating folks are
typically ignored until right to the end
where you want to deploy or you know put
your system into production and then you
have all these kinds of surprises where
they said are you kind of operate this
we're not supporting this or that
technology so having them involved all
the time it's probably useful thing
absolutely then there would be the
second step so once you want you to see
the expectations and perform this
preparatory work the next step is to
find out who all the stakeholders are
and figure out what their their concerns
and their goals as far as the
architectures concerned are so you
should also look beyond way beyond IT
find all the all the business the
business stakeholders and there are some
some typical
roles that get left out the one that you
already mentioned will be the app Ops
guys typically they get left out they
don't have a big say though they will be
the ones receiving the the page in the
middle of the night to go and replace
the CPU board and another class of
stakeholders that get left out typically
from these these evaluations are the
developers who will be maintaining the
architecture once it is developed and
deployed typically typically that's a
different group but although they have a
stake in the architecture and how easy
would it be to maintain the architecture
how easy would it be to localize
problems and fix and modify areas and so
on they are not represented typically
often they're not even yet known at this
time that's right Molly that's right so
when many instances when you ask for a
list of the stakeholders people don't
really have anything ready um based on
my experience at at times even if they
have it ready this list is incomplete or
outdated so should you find yourself in
a similar situation my recommendation
would be to revisit this list and go
demotius again and make sure revalidated
basically make sure that everybody who
should be on the list is on the list now
and that you get to meet them all
otherwise it it is impossible for you to
to establish a connection with the
architecture stakeholders who will help
you in establishing
the violation criteria that's that's
basically the whole idea behind
architecture evaluation and stakeholder
involvement you will use you'll leverage
the stakeholders to define a custom in
violation criteria that varies from from
architecture to architecture because the
architecture supports all these
stakeholders and you can't really pull
out a set of cand relation criteria and
measure architectures against these can
criteria they are defined for each
architecture with a stakeholder another
thing another thing that you need to do
is to sense whether the architecture has
been commissioned just for show because
knowing that gives you insight into the
relationship that you have or you won't
be able to have with the stakeholders
sometimes and this is sad but true
sometimes you get called in to perform
an architecture evaluation just to to
justify decisions that have been already
made or things that people are building
already so this is like if you want some
statistics and a statistical analysis
you'll always find out what the customer
wants to have so if the customer says
you know this is a great architecture
please convince our critics that this is
great and that's a different situation
as if you have to do an objective
evaluation that's right so typically
what happens you get called in to
evaluate an architecture and as you
start figuring out the the landscape and
who the stakeholders are what are the
business drivers behind the architecture
and so on you will realize that the
architecture construction stage has
started already and you got called in
them in the middle because due to
increased pressures or schedule slipping
or questions about the whole the whole
project someone wants to find to find a
justification for their building the
architecture or find an objective
endorsement for for their building the
architecture and the quality of the
architecture and of course if this is
the case I'm not saying you shouldn't do
the architecture valuation you should
your goal is to help whoever is building
the architecture and making sure yes
well that's that depends sometimes you
may turn them down even if they offered
to pay if these prerequisites that we
covered are not available and they would
not help you to
to satisfy them you should just walk out
yeah but the the idea here is that you
if you understand exactly the forces
behind the architecture evaluation you
would have a better better grip on your
relationship with the stakeholders yeah
because it's very different if you step
into a project where they just need an
objective third-party evaluation for
things that have been decided or or
commissioned already yeah a lot of
psychology also absolutely absolutely
there are many traits that you would
notice one of the most common ones is
that if the are if the art evaluation
has been commissioned for show not
everybody it will welcome the evaluation
team and this has happened to me more
than one time whenever this happens to
you know try to establish a good
relationship with these folks and
explain to them that you are not there
to take the job or to prove that they're
wrong you were there to to help help
them identify risk early on and help
them that big help them provide a you
know of working architecture at the end
of the day so you will help them look
better when when everything settles yeah
so how do you perform the evaluation
itself I mean of course we talked about
looking at the architectural documents
at interviewing stakeholders talking
with them and it will support available
it's kind of the obvious question no
unfortunately this is an area that needs
a lot of work if you are an architect
and you're looking for options as far as
tools are concerned you can find quite a
few options out there if your developer
you're looking for an ID or other
development tools you have lots of
options if you're a tester you have lots
of options but what options do you have
if you're an evaluator not not a whole
lot I'm aware of very few maybe a couple
of products that claim that they are
architectural relation products though
if you take a closer look at them
they're not quite there yet they're it's
a big step forward and the reason I'm
saying that another not there yet is
that most of the analysis that they help
you with our static so they would
analyze the static structure the static
dependencies between the modules
tomography like that yes exactly like
like the likes after tomography and
there are there's not a product I'm
aware of but there's a same thing but
also it works on source code so it can
be used only in later stages it expects
that there already is code to analyze
it's right that you talked about this
right Plus that kind of product and in
the other that I'm thinking of is the
same problem works only for
architectures where you have the source
code for the entire thing well in real
life if you're looking at enterprise
applications you have after shelf
components that you don't have the
source query with what you have legacy
components that even if you have the
source code for nobody understands it or
these tools won't be able to parse and
find yeah you have outside vendors that
provide you with a service interface or
something like that that you're using
and these tools would be with fall short
in helping you expand the analysis
nobody on these boundaries and also what
I found I just saw a presentation on
some of these tools these days and what
I found a bit strange was obviously they
can only work on the abstractions that
are somehow represented in the code like
package dependencies class dependencies
and yes you can define things like
subsystems using directories or
something but there is no architectural
meta model with rich definitions of the
concepts and buildings blocks building
blocks you have available so the the the
conformity of the code of checking
whether the code conforms to a certain
architecture is very limited to a number
of limited concepts that's right these
tool these tools tend to require you're
defining some constraints and then they
verify that information that they can
pull out of the source code meets or
doesn't meet these constraints the the
key challenge with these tools though
remember from back to to the beginning
of our conversation as far as
architecture is concerned these tools
don't tell you anything about how these
components communicate at runtime so the
fact that I have a dependency that
doesn't manage any constraints between
two modules doesn't mean that
architectural misses sound what if what
if the communication between these two
modules is very expensive and then I
like it is that distributed right and
I'm looking I have a very very expensive
channel between the two components
and I'm looking at a
the cheating performance that's measured
with sub-second response in sub-second
response times or some high throughput
well those tools are not gonna help me
figure out this problem so the only
tools are probably gonna help you are
like the generic tools like wiki's Excel
maybe a requirements management tool to
sort through the requirements that's
right in the absent in the absence of
tools you're stuck with without without
any tool support for architecture
evaluation but no not don't give up I
have successfully used generic tools for
architecture evaluation and there's a
set of ubiquitous tools that the chances
that they are already installed on
people's computers are very high and
they would be word I used word templates
very successfully for architecture
evaluation and capturing evaluation
scenarios Excel used it very
successfully for also capturing the
outcome of the analysis and presenting
graphs that show different different
things coming out of the architecture
relation even Visio they're people who
know how to use Visio I know
non-technical people otherwise who knows
know how to use Visio and they would be
able to sketch a diagram or a graph that
you're interested in seeing and using
the generic tools besides the fact that
chances are very high that people
already have them on their computers is
another advantage and that is a very
very low learning curve most of the
times that is zero at a time there may
be some some hand-holding a little bit
to give them stuck going with filling in
some templates that he provided but
that's all about it there are no
licensing implications if these if the
people have office installed or or any
other generic tools and they're they're
there they're there to help yet another
thing that I recommend doing and I could
give some examples with tools that I
have been successful with is the the use
of other generic tools that may not be
part of this common ubiquitous set but
people are likely to have such as such
as mind map diagrams oh yeah one of the
artifacts that comes up in when you
perform evaluations that followed the
architecture trade-off analysis method
which is one of the methods from the sei
about this in a minute again it's called
a utility tree and this utility tree
imagine a tree slanted 90 degrees
counterclockwise so the root is on the
right on the left hand side and then it
expands with the Leafs on the right hand
side and it shows you the architecture
goes and refines them and then it goes
down two scenarios well a mind map
diagram is very very useful for
capturing all this information in any
mind mapping tool would help you put up
these diagrams very nicely with the
advantage you can collapse selectively
collapse nodes and navigate and so on so
keep your eyes open for any other tool
any other generic tool that though it
hasn't been thought of as a tool for
architecture evaluation so will be handy
one could argue that architecture
evaluation is mainly about structure is
structuring and systematizing
information it ought to have it
evaluated so all kinds of tools that
help you structuring information are
probably useful well again this is a
representation of an abstraction we're
abstracting out a selection criterion
evaluation criteria in depending on the
tools we can use a particular
representation or another the utility
tree makes it easy to see to have a big
picture with these are my architecture
concerns and this is how they boil down
into concrete scenarios evaluation with
outside of a particular context is
meaningless because in some context the
particular value for response time would
be would be good whereas in a lot of
context would would be appalling so it
utility tree and all these artifacts
help you articulate the evaluation
criteria in concrete concrete context so
that's maybe briefly talk about the ATM
the architectural trade-off analysis
method right it's also some stuff the
sei folks came up with what is it and is
it useful the sei folks have been
working in this space for over a decade
and they have produced quite a few
methods I think the first and the oldest
that comes to mind is Sam the software
architecture analysis method and this is
a method that caters to evaluating
modify ability and flexibility and it's
particularly useful when you want to do
a side by side comparison there are
methods coming from the same group a
ta M stands for the architecture
trade-off analysis method which is a
successor of Sam and focuses on
trade-offs made by various design
decisions made by the architect when
when they picked one solution versus
another yeah and another one that comes
to mind is quite quite popular is the
sebum the cost benefits analysis method
which takes over where where the ATM
method stops and plugs in economical
factors as well so you have you have
evaluated and you have identified a set
of architecture strategies for meeting
some goals some quality goals for the
architecture then the question that you
ask well can I pay for all these things
are costs associated with everything for
example you could integrate with a bus
you can integrate with a broker and you
want to see well what is the cost
associated with each of these options
not it makes it makes technical sense
and it's where see BAM comes into place
and and how is ATM different from what
you just talked about is there any
specifics that go beyond what we just
talked about generically the points that
I covered so far are applicable across
several methods I have distilled these
these points from evaluation using Sam
as well as ATM what these methods have
in common is that they're all scenario
based evaluation methods you're not
gonna get a very precise answer it's not
not like a simulator that you you plug
in a description like a description of a
circuit and then you simulate and you
get very precise measurements this is
more of a back-of-the-envelope let's
identify the architecture risk and and
see whether the design decisions made
are supporting the the architecture
goals so that's what all the methods
have in common they use scenarios is is
a vehicle for exploring and pressure
testing various parts of the
architecture otherwise they have
slightly different goals though ATM
focuses on trade-offs Sam on modify
ability and sebum on the economics let
me let me try to to connect this to some
of the stuff I'm working in
model driven development now I see
obviously in this architecture
evaluation there are two aspects one is
checking whether an architecture
conforms the requirements and the
stakeholders opinions and these kinds of
things formalization probably won't help
there because we have to talk to people
but on the other side if you want to
find out whether like for example if you
have like these two components and
they're distributed and still there is
timing requirements it's a good idea to
distribute them cost performance wise
would it help in your opinion if the
architecture was really formally defined
by having a meta model that defines the
concepts and abstractions like what is
the component what's the message q how
do we define an interface how do you
associate component instances with
computing notes or whatever and then if
you'd have instances of that meta model
ie models that actually really show
there is this component of these
operations would that help in analyzing
the technical aspects of the
architecture evaluation obviously not
the more people oriented ones but would
that be useful so so would a more
structured and formal approach to
describing a systems architecture not in
terms of source code but in terms of
higher level abstractions would that
make this stuff simpler certainly and
there's a matter of fact when you
perform either Sam or ATM and you're
looking at particular architecture goals
like performance you have the luxury of
employing some of the theory that is
available in this space to analyze
performance for example and you would
you would use obviously use queueing
Theory where there's a small set of
parameters like the arrival rate and so
on that if you can figure out what they
are then there's a set of techniques
that would help you modify them and get
get to levels that are you are within
your goals however the challenge with
with the generic system that you're
evaluating is that there are so many
choices and options it's very hard to
come up with a model that that would
cover everything so what happens for
other architectures let's say for
architectures of for embedded systems or
four four four four small domains for
those domains you can actually have it
models exist already and there you can
get a better a much better value
that means that machines can be
simulated easily this right you can get
a better a better evaluation for
particular domains where you have models
available the the challenge with that
though is that that a small that is a
small number of domains and typically
these are no telecom switches or things
that people have been building over and
over again you know the requirements you
know the typical problems and in the
typical quality goals that you're
interested in and you have these models
available however for your generic you
know application enterprise application
that you're involved with it's it's hard
to come up with a model because they're
so the variability is so high so what
you do you isolate particular areas like
performance or security we do we may
employ a thread model or queueing theory
for performance and so on and use these
modeling techniques in selected areas
where you can actually go and drill into
actually i'm i work in these kinds of
areas I actually try to do this in a
model first approach and then generate
stuff from the models so that you can do
meaningful analysis on the model level
and that in my view and my experience
this actually is a big step of course if
you have the wrong meta models and the
wrong models this is still a bad
architecture so you still have to do the
evaluation but you might have higher
level abstractions on which to evaluate
that's right this right the the the more
areas you can model in the architecture
the more accurate your your results are
going to be right okay so let's come
back to this point we talked about we we
just briefly visited in the beginning
which was agile so if you say you want
to evaluate the architecture before
doing all the work and implementing it
how does this go together with a you
know we don't need architects we're all
just a bunch of happy developers saying
where the architecture evolves over time
well back to your last statement that I
think even even the people behind XP
like Kent Beck have reviewed their
statement that architects are not within
don't have any place next P in the
second edition of their book but
typically what what happens on agile
projects I tend to recommend
architecture valuation right at the end
of iteration zero where you have spiked
a few areas and they have an approximate
idea of
how your system is going to look like
you've made a few components elections
you've made a few design decisions you
know you're in a good position now to
pressure test these decisions you verify
that your assumption are correct
the design is interview you've you've
made our sound and so on so let me let
me try and draw a parallel between
between agile and architecture
evaluation the one thing that we covered
quickly earlier about architecture
evaluation is stakeholder involvement
yeah well if you look at it what XP and
agile development on screeches and
recommends they recommend the developers
working hand-in-hand with good customers
so you're involving the stakeholders
whenever you are availa new york attach
is just extrapolating the same principle
to the architecture land another area
and I haven't talked about that yet but
this is a good good time to bring it up
is that if you look at extreme
programming
you always have tests you start with
tests and you have what what the success
criteria is and then you're going to
write code towards meeting that the the
success criteria towards your having to
the test yes well for scenario based
architecture valuation one of the key
elements that you capture for each
scenario is what is the response measure
what kind of of response do you expect
the arc from the architecture to declare
that you have met this performance
criteria you have met the security
criteria so drawing a parallel between
the two again you see that having the
scenarios would correspond to cards two
stories however you want to call them
and each of these scenarios has a
measure that corresponds to the test so
you can think of doing architecture
evaluation is is employing TDD at the
architecture level here are some goals
that I want to meet and I'm going to
don't do it before you don't afterwards
or as you go along it's not like that
your first evaluating and then
implementing is like it's in test-driven
development you first write the test and
write the code that's right if you're
evaluating the architecture you are
employing it after the fact right
however in an ideal world and this is
what I would what I'm hoping to see once
people start embracing architecture more
in a different manner tape into
architecture so far is you sit down with
the architect and start writing up the
scenarios and they say wait a minute I
already have this stuff and they open
their drawer and they will see all the
scenarios because the techniques that
have discussed so far assembling
scenarios articulating how you measure
the architecture meeting these measures
and so on are not restricted to
evaluation per se that's what I do for
design as well so in an ideal world the
architect would have that already and it
would be a done deal and I would be a
happy evaluator when it happens probably
it doesn't happen too often okay is
there anything else you want to say
about architecture evaluation the the
whole agile how is this not waterfall
area comes up over and over again and so
I'm glad the week we covered it but I
hope that by now you and in others who
are listening to us we have noticed the
parallel between architecture valuation
and agile development have seen the
value in in verifying these design
choices early on for for the interest in
the interest of saving cost and not not
having developers work on things that
will end up being thrown out the other
area that I wanted to mention here which
is also important in unfortunately
neglected on most projects is the
capturing of constraints and assumptions
as you assemble these scenarios you will
start growing a list these are
assumptions that we've made and this
list will grow and will grow is is you
evaluate the architecture in while at
the beginning that mustn't that may not
come in is very useful it's like writing
unit tests at the beginning the ROI is
low but is you have is the number of
tests increases then you can you you're
in a much better position to go off and
refactor your code well same thing with
architecture once you start growing this
list of assumptions as soon as something
changes the requirements change the
business environment changes the
technical environment changes you go
back to your over your list of
assumptions and see okay which of my
assumptions have been invalidated if you
find anything you trace back to the
architecture violation scenarios that
where you made these assumptions and
rerun the analysis and and see whether
it is worth your going back to the
drawing board to
maybe redesign a piece or or revisit a
design decision or not so this is a very
important aspect that many people are
not aware of and projects fail because
of wrong assumptions okay so we before
we wrap up I'd like to mention that
we're actually doing this at the cello
conference in in in Aarhus in Denmark
and we just had lunch together and
during lunch we talked about how we
could increase the sales numbers of a
book we wrote together which is the plop
d5 book so I thought let's just put in a
plaque quickly so maybe just you know
just describe the plop t-54 briefly and
why people should get it hmm
so a plop d5 is the most recent
installment of the plop D series which
gathers best patterned papers submitted
at plop conferences and the two of us
with with James we worked hard on
assembling an interesting melange of
patterns of patent papers in plop d5 and
we have some interesting areas there's
always the area of Telecom which I had a
very interesting discussion earlier
today over breakfast with the someone
else here jello which revolved around
Telecom in how we always run up to the
telecom systems to find inspiration
whenever we need to deal with
high-performance systems whenever we
need to do to deal with high
availability systems whenever we need to
deal with large scale systems and so on
so you're saying these patterns are not
just interesting for telecom folks but
rather
this right because people go and knock
on the telecom door whenever they run
into problems that have been solved in
the telecom world years ago and only now
with our building distributed
applications and supporting lots and
lots of users we're running into there
are some other interesting areas their
patents on writing patterns which a lot
of people are doing these days there are
parents on making systems very flexible
like applying ideas from prototype based
languages into into systems that are
built with regular object owning
languages like Java or C sharp yeah and
what does the you remember from the book
it's been a while that's actually the
problem
I think what's interesting in that
patterns community as a trend is that
we're kind of going away from these
design pattern II kind of things that we
all know from the Gulf book so if you
want to see how the community developed
and what areas patterns have penetrated
into and and whether useful I think that
the flop d5 book as well as some of the
other flop T 1 2 3 & 4 obviously give
you a good overview so that's certainly
an interesting aspect to and the other
thing that it's worth mentioning now is
the the way the plot the books have
changed so if you look at the first
books first two books you see most of
the submissions model two chapters in
the book are individual patterns right
as you go as you go to plop-plop d 4 and
plot D 5 now the majority of headline
chapters are pattern languages so is the
field has matured and people have a
better understanding of the power of
patterns how to use patterns and all the
right patterns we have shifted from
individual patterns to pattern languages
and to the relationships and the
connections between patterns that have
been harvested from from different
domains yeah so in short consider
getting the book I think for each of
them this gives us the equivalent of one
kind of beer I guess so we're not
getting rich from that but spreading the
message is probably useful yep
definitely
ok Drago's thanks for being on the show
and thank you we'll be in touch yep
right bye bye
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license
see the software engineer a do website
for details